Welcome. This tutorial covers the daily RP Rental workflow now migrated from manual steps into Odoo.
Odoo is the source of truth for customers, equipment, availability, contracts, deliveries, returns, quality checks, and billing.
If it is not in Odoo, it did not happen. Keep every step updated as you work.
Start from the main Apps menu. Use the global search bar to quickly find Customers, Rentals, and Products.
Your role controls what you can do. If a button is missing, request access instead of working around the process.
Before creating a quote, confirm the customer exists and the billing and delivery contacts are correct.
Create new customers only when needed. Add phone, email, addresses, and set any payment terms required by the business.
Rental products represent what you sell. Rental assets represent the physical units that get delivered and returned.
Use the imported catalog and product codes to search quickly. Confirm the item is marked as rentable and available.
Always confirm availability for the requested dates before promising equipment to the customer.
Create a new quotation for the customer, then add the rental products and set the rental start and end dates.
Set the rental period before validating pricing. Dates drive availability and the correct rental price calculation.
Pricing follows the imported rate matrix. Confirm daily, weekly, and monthly cycles align with the agreed commercial terms.
When the customer approves, confirm the quotation. This becomes the rental contract and triggers the operational workflow.
Review the delivery order, ensure the correct warehouse and destination, and prepare assets for dispatch.
Validate the delivery in Odoo when the equipment leaves. Record any required evidence and confirm the on-site location.
If dates or quantities change, update the contract immediately. Do not track changes only in chat or email.
If an asset is replaced, record the exchange so traceability and billing remain correct.
For partial returns, process the return picking and adjust the contract lines so invoicing stays accurate.
When all equipment returns, validate the return picking. This is the handoff into quality control.
Run the Rental Return inspection. Capture condition notes and issues so maintenance and billing decisions are supported.
Before sending equipment out again, complete the Ready-To-Rent inspection. This prevents avoidable failures in the field.
Billing is driven by the contract and time. Generate invoices based on the agreed billing cadence.
If your process uses the 3-3-3 rule, apply it consistently: daily, weekly, and monthly billing logic must match the contract.
Create the invoice from the rental order, review line items and taxes, then send it to the customer from Odoo.
When payment is received, register it and reconcile. Keep Accounting accurate so reporting stays reliable.
Use reports to monitor open rentals, asset utilization, overdue returns, invoices due, and quality backlog.
Once the rental is fully returned, quality is completed, and invoicing is done, close the loop and archive evidence.
You are ready to run the daily workflow in Odoo using your real catalog, assets, and rates.